Guide to the John Jacob Scherer Papers, 1931-1959
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Jacob Scherer papers 1931-1959
Scherer, John Jacob, 1881-1956.
4.8 linear feet Extent: 4,000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01146
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Jacob Scherer Papers (1931-1959) were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1979.
Biographical Note
1881, May 6 Born, Marion, Va.
1888-1897 Student, Marion College
1897-1898 Student, Fishburne Military School, Waynesboro, Va.
1900 Earned A.B., Roanoke College, Salem Va.
1904 Earned B.D. Gettysberg (Pa.) Lutheran Theological Seminary Ordained into the Evangelical Lutheran Church
1904-1906 Minister, Grace Lutheran Church, Fairmont, W. Va.
1906- Minister, First Evangelical Lutheran Church, Richmond, VA
1906, Dec. 13 Married Anna Belle Downtain
1916- Associate justice Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court, Richmond, Va.
1919 Conferred, D.D., Roanoke College, Salem, Va.
1926-1948 President, Lutheran Synod of Virginia
1946 Member of the American Arbitration Association
1956, Jan. 14 Died, Richmond, Va.
John Jacob Scherer, Jr. served and held positions in many civic and community organizations including: President and member of Board of Directors, Richmond Community Council; Trustee, Roanoke College, Marion Junior College, and Richmond Professional Institute of College of William and Mary (founder and President); Konnarock Training School (Director); and Iron Mountain School for Boys. Scherer also served as a member of the Evangelical Lutheran Synod of Virginia (President 1919-1922) and Lutheran Synod of Virginia (President 1926-1948). Scherer also served on the National War Labor Board, Region IV; as Vice-Chairman of the National Wage Stabilization Board, Region IV; and as Chairman of the Virginia Board of Public Welfare.
Collection Overview
The John Jacob Scherer (1881-1956) Papers span the years 1931 to 1959. They chiefly consist of subject files and printed material but also include writings, sermons, clippings, and subject cards. The collection primarily relates to Scherer's career as an independent labor arbitrator for several companies and labor unions in Virginia including: Mead Corporation, United Paper Workers of America, Brooks Transfer Company, and the Teamsters Union. Included are two volumes of typed transcripts of proceedings of arbitration cases. Other areas represented in the collection are Scherer's career as a Lutheran minister in both West Virginia and Virginia. There is no information pertaining to his personal life or his tenure as an associate justice. In the Subject Files Series is information pertaining to labor arbitration from 1937-1955, such as literature from both labor unions and the companies. This information contains the grievances of each party, and also contains Scherer's notes and recommendations for specific cases. The Printed Materials Series contains published texts collected by Scherer that pertain to labor arbitration. The Miscellaneous Series includes Scherer's writings on labor arbitration and also a few sermons and church addresses. Photocopied newspaper clippings in this series concern both Scherer's labor arbitration and ministry.
Subject Headings
Mead Corporation; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; United Paper Workers of America; Brooks Transfer Company; Arbitration, Industrial -- Virginia; Arbitration, Industrial -- West Virginia; Arbitrators, Industrial -- Virginia; Arbitrators, Industrial -- West Virginia; Lutheran Church -- Sermons; Lutheran Church -- Clergy
Contents of Collection
- Subject Files Series, 1937-1956, undated 1945-1955)
  - Subject Cards, 1940-1949(Includes Subject Files information) (Box 1)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1945-1955, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Ampthill Rayon Workers, 1944-1950, undated (Box 1)
  - Baltimore Transfer Company, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Bristol Steel and Iron Works, Inc., 1954-1955, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Background information on Scherer, John Jacob, Jr., 1947-1956, undated (Box 1)
  - Brooks Transportation Company, 1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America
    - 1945-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Brunswick-Balke-Collender Company, 1949-1955, undated (Box 1)
  - Celanese Corporation of America, 1945-1952 (Box 1)
  - Celanese Corporation of America: (Box 2)
    - Case Nos.:
      - L-436, WAS-L-23-48; 1948-1949, undated (Box 2)
      - L-5067, WAS-L-14-49;1949, undated (Box 2)
  - Citizens Rapid Transit Company, Court Exhibits 1-36, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Clarksburg, W. Va., 1954-1955, undated (Box 2)
  - Concrete Pipe and Products Co. Inc., 1947-1949, undated (Box 2)
  - Consolidated Paper and Box Manufacturing Company, 1947-1952, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: General, 1943-1955 (Box 2)
  - Craddock-Terry Shoe Corporation, 1945, undated (Box 2)
  - Davidson Transfer and Storage Company, 1952-1954, undated (Box 2)
  - East Coast Freight Lines, 1950 (Box 2)
  - E.I. Dupont de Nemours and Company, 1955, undated (Box 2)
  - Erwin Mills and Textiles Workers Union of America, 1950-1951, undated (Box 3)
  - Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Fiber Board Container Company, 1946-1952, undated (Box 3)
  - Friedman-Marks Clothing Co. Inc., 1937-1954, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Hoffmeister Concrete Company, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Huntington Chair Corporation, 1949-1954, undated (Box 3)
  - Indiana-Kansas City Motor Express Company, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Industrial Relations Research Association, 1948-1950 (Box 3)
  - International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, 1953-1955, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Jefferson Manufacturing Co. Inc., 1947 (Box 4)
  - Jones and Robins, Inc. and Brown Realty Corporation, 1943-1954 (Box 4)
  - Kaufman and Company, Inc., 1953-1954, undated (Box 4)
  - Kingan and Company, 1939-1941, undated (Box 4)
  - Laburnum Construction Company, 1949-1953, undated (Box 4)
  - Larus and Brother Company, Inc., 1944-1946, undated (Box 4)
  - Lummis and Company, 1951, undated (Box 4)
  - Manchester Board and Paper Company, Inc., 1946-1948, undated (Box 4)
  - Mead Corporation, 1946-1947, undated (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Arbitrators, 1947-1952, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Arbitrators, 1953, undated (Box 5)
  - National Electrical Contractors Association, Inc., 1947-1951, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - National Gupsum Company:
    - Kimbalton, Va., 1954-1955, undated (Box 5)
    - Petersburg, Va., 1947-1955 (Box 5)
    - Roanoke, Va., 1946-1953, undated (Box 5)
  - National War Labor Board, 1943-1955, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Old Hickory Chemical Company, 1948-1949, undated (Box 6)
  - Planters Nut and Chocolate Company, 1948-1955 (Box 6)
  - R. C. Motor Lines, Inc., 1955 (Box 6)
  - R. H. Hardesty Company, 1951, undated (Box 6)
  - Richmond Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, 1949-1950, undated (Box 6)
  - Richmond Dairy Company, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Richmond-Greyhound Lines Inc., 1953-1955, undated (Box 6)
  - Richmond Hotels, Inc., 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - Ripplemead Lime Company, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Roanoke-Webster Brick Co. Inc., 1950-1955, undated (Box 6)
  - Savage Truck Line Inc., 1946-1951, undated (Box 6)
  - Southern Aid Society of Virginia, Incorporated., 1947-1948, undated (Box 6)
  - Standard Lime and Stone Company, 1949-1952, undated (Box 6)
  - Standard Paper Manufacturing Co., 1950-1955 (Box 6)
  - Swift and Company, 1943-1945, undated (Box 7)
  - Swift Ice Cream Company of Hampton, Va., 1946 (Box 7)
  - T and E Laundry Co. Inc., 1944-1945 (Box 7)
  - Torch Club, 1952-1953, undated (Box 7)
  - Union Envelope Company, 1948-1951, undated (Box 7)
  - Virginia Dairy Company, Inc., 1951, undated (Box 7)
  - Virginia Electric and Power company, 1948-1953;Union Exhibits #1-17,1948 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Manufacturer's Association, Inc., 1954-1955, undated (Box 7)
  - Virginia Mechanical Corporation, 1950, undated (Box 7)
  - Virginia Telephone and Telegraph Co., 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Transit Company, 1943-1946, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Wage Stabilization Board, 1951-1952,June, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - West Virginia Pulp and Paper Company, 1947-1948 (Box 8)
  - Wilson Trucking Company, 1954, undated (Box 8)
  - Wortendyke Manufacturing Company, 1948-1949, undated (Box 8)
  - Yale and Towne Manufacturing Co., 1952-1953, undated (Box 8)
  - Yellow Cab Company, 1949-1953 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1955, undated (Box 8)
- Printed Material Series, 1931-1955
  - 1931-1948, (6 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1949-1953, (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1954-1955, (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1955, undated(1 folder, 1 vol.) (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1931-1959, undated
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 12)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1931-1959, undated, (2 folders)
  - Writings and speeches (Box 12)
- Newspaper Clippings Series, 1934-1955, undated
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 12)
- Oversize Materials Series
  - Subject Files (Oversize-box 15)
    - Planters Nut and Chocolate Company, 1948-1955 (Oversize-box 15)